Guide to the Louise Talma Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Louise Talma papers
1942-1985
1952-1963
YCAL MSS 811
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
11.31
(37 boxes)
The Louise Talma Papers contain materials relating to composition and performance of Talma's opera The Alcestiad, and to Thornton Wilder, his friendship with Talma, and his collaboration with her as librettist for The Alcestiad. Contents relating to The Alcestiad, 1950s-1970s, include autograph letters, signed, to Talma from Thornton Wilder, 1952-1975 and undated, and from his sister Isabel Wilder, 1954-1972, with some letters annotated by Talma; autograph manuscript music drafts; diazo reproductions of autograph manuscript full scores and vocal scores, including a German translation by Herberth E. Herlitschka; microfilms of scores; autograph manuscript drafts by Wilder of the libretto, and typescript mimeograph copies of the libretto; audiocassettes and reel-to-reel audiotapes of performances, 1960-1962 and undated; photographs of performances; and clippings of reviews. Other papers, 1940s-1980s, include scores and parts for other vocal, orchestral, and chamber works by Talma, most diazo reproductions of autograph manuscript scores, 1947-1980 and undated; other writings by Wilder, most typescript, 1953-1973 and undated; clippings relating to Wilder; concert programs and other printed material, most concerning performances of Talma's music; and photographs, most of Talma with Wilder or with musicians, 1956-1962.
Talma, Louise, 1906-1996
Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Louise Talma, 1997.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 23 (audiocassettes) and boxes 24-27 (reel-to-reel audiotapes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Louise Talma (1906-1996)
Louise Talma (1906-1996), American composer. Talma composed The Alcestiad, an opera in three acts, with libretto by Thornton Wilder, in 1955-1958. The opera premiered in German translation in Frankfurt, Germany, on 1962 March 1.
Scope and Contents
The Louise Talma Papers contain materials relating to composition and performance of Talma's opera The Alcestiad, and to Thornton Wilder, his friendship with Talma, and his collaboration with her as librettist for The Alcestiad. Contents relating to The Alcestiad, 1950s-1970s, include autograph letters, signed, to Talma from Thornton Wilder, 1952-1975 and undated, and from his sister Isabel Wilder, 1954-1972, with some letters annotated by Talma; autograph manuscript music drafts; diazo reproductions of autograph manuscript full scores and vocal scores, including a German translation by Herberth E. Herlitschka; microfilms of scores; autograph manuscript drafts by Wilder of the libretto, and typescript mimeograph copies of the libretto; audiocassettes and reel-to-reel audiotapes of performances, 1960-1962 and undated; photographs of performances; and clippings of reviews. Other papers, 1940s-1980s, include scores and parts for other vocal, orchestral, and chamber works by Talma, most diazo reproductions of autograph manuscript scores, 1947-1980 and undated; other writings by Wilder, most typescript, 1953-1973 and undated; clippings relating to Wilder; concert programs and other printed material, most concerning performances of Talma's music; and photographs, most of Talma with Wilder or with musicians, 1956-1962.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1942-1975. II. The Alcestiad, 1952-1976. III. Other Papers, 1947-1985.
Chamber music -- Scores; Composers -- United States -- Archives; Operas -- Librettos; Operas -- Scores; Orchestral music -- Scores; Vocal music -- Scores; Audiocassettes -- United States -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Sound recordings -- United States -- 20th Century; Tape reels -- United States -- 20th Century; Composers -- United States -- 20th Century; Herlitschka, Herberth E., 1893-1970; Talma, Louise, 1906-1996; Talma, Louise, 1906-1996 ( Alcestiad); Wilder, Isabel, 1900-1995; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975 -- Musical settings
- Correspondence, 1942-1975, undated; Series I; 3.13; (8 boxes)
  - Wilder, Isabel, 1954-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1952-1956 April (Box 1, Folder 8-14)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1956 May-1957 May (Box 2, Folder 15-26)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1957 June-1958 May (Box 3, Folder 27-38)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1958 June-1959 December (Box 4, Folder 39-49)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1960 January-1961 April (Box 5, Folder 50-61)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1961 April-1963 December (Box 6, Folder 62-72)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1964 January-1975 December (Box 7, Folder 73-83)
  - Wilder, Thornton, undated (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Wilder, Thornton (excerpts). Photocopies, undated (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Wilder, Thornton (excerpts). Transcriptions, typescript mimeograph, undated (Box 8, Folder 86-87)
  - Unidentified, 1942-1964, undated (Box 8, Folder 88-89)
- The Alcestiad, 1952-1976, undated; Series II; 6.09; (20 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into five subseries: Libretto, Music, German Translation, Sound Recordings, and Other Papers
  - Libretto
    Scope and Contents
    Autograph manuscript by Thornton Wilder, unless otherwise noted
    - Act I. Draft, 1955-1959, undated (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - Acts I-II. Draft, undated (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - Act II. Draft, undated (Box 9, Folder 92)
    - Act II. Draft, "final version", 1957 (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Act III. Draft, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 94)
    - Acts I-III. Typescript carbon, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - Act I. Typescript mimeograph stencils, undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 96)
    - Act II. Typescript mimeograph stencils, undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 97)
    - Act III. Typescript mimeograph stencils, undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 98-99)
    - Acts I-III. Typescript mimeograph, 1962; (4 copies) (Box 11, Folder 100-101)
    - Acts I-III. Typescript mimeograph, 1962; (16 copies) (Box 12, Folder 102-109)
    - Acts I-III. Typescript mimeograph, 1962; (14 copies) (Box 13, Folder 110-116)
    - Acts I-III. Typescript mimeograph, 1962; (14 copies) (Box 14, Folder 117-123)
    - Acts I-III. Typescript mimeograph, 1962; (11 copies) (Box 15, Folder 124-129)
    - Act I, excerpts. Typescript mimeograph, 1963; (13 copies) (Box 15, Folder 130-131)
  - Music
    Autograph manuscript by Louise Talma, unless otherwise noted
    - Notes and sketches, 1952-1960, undated (Box 16 (Oversize), Folder 132-133)
    - Act I. Drafts, 1956 January-1957 January (Box 16 (Oversize), Folder 134)
    - Act II. Drafts, 1957 February-December (Box 16 (Oversize), Folder 135)
    - Act III. Drafts, 1958 February-October (Box 16 (Oversize), Folder 136)
    - Act I. Full score, excerpts (diazo reproduction), undated (Box 16 (Oversize), Folder 137)
    - Act I. Full score (diazo reproduction, with annotations), 1959 August 19 (Box 17 (Oversize), Folder 138-139)
      In 2 volumes
    - Act II. Full score (diazo reproduction, with annotations), 1960 November 3 (Box 18 (Oversize), Folder 140)
    - Act III. Full score (diazo reproduction, with annotations), 1960 December 24 (Box 18 (Oversize), Folder 141)
    - Act I. Full score, "corrected" (microfilm), 1975-1976; (1 reel) (Box 19, Folder 142)
      "Hunter College copy"
      "For making the transparencies for Carl Fisher, Inc."
    - Acts II-III. Full score, "corrected" (microfilm), 1975-1976; (1 reel) (Box 19, Folder 143)
    - Act I. Vocal score (diazo reproduction, "uncorrected," with annotations), 1957 February 23 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 144)
    - Act II.Vocal score (diazo reproduction, "uncorrected," with annotations), undated (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 145)
    - Act III. Vocal score (diazo reproduction, "uncorrected," with annotations), 1958 October 30 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 146)
    - Acts I-III. Vocal score (diazo reproduction, "corrected through page 102," with annotations), 1958 October 30 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 147)
    - Acts I-III. Vocal score (diazo reproduction, "corrected," with annotations), 1958 October 30 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 148)
  - German translation
    - Libretto. Notes and score (diazo reproduction), with translation, undated (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 149)
    - Libretto. "Text Korrigenda" (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 150)
    - Libretto, German translation. Typescript mimeograph, 1957 July 23 (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 151)
    - Act I. Vocal score (diazo reproduction, with annotations), 1957 February 23; 4 (Box 22 (Oversize), Folder 152)
    - Acts I-III. Vocal score (diazo reproduction, with annotations), 1958 October 30 (Box 22 (Oversize), Folder 153)
    - Acts I-III. Vocal scores (diazo reproduction, "errata not corrected," with annotations), 1958 October 30; (3 copies) (Box 22 (Oversize), Folder 154-156)
  - Sound recordings
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - First performance (1 of 2 audiocassettes), 1962 March 1; 1; 01:31:03; The program is distorted at times. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002091243494)
    - First performance (2 of 2 audiocassettes), 1962 March 1; 1; 00:53:16; The program is distorted at times. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002091243502)
    - Second performance (1 of 2 audiocassettes), 1962 March 3; 1; 01:31:30; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002091243510)
    - Second performance (2 of 2 audiocassettes), 1962 March 3; 1; 00:54:09; The program is distorted at times. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002091243528)
    - Act I / Act II (1 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1; 01:58:50; The program is distorted at times. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002091243536)
    - Act III (2 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1; 00:27:15 (Box 23, Item barcode 39002091243544)
    - Act I / Act II (1 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1; 01:56:49; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002091243551)
    - Act III, undated; 1; 00:26:42 (Box 23, Item barcode 39002091243569)
    - Act I. Master tape, English and German, 1961 November - December; 1; 00:59:47; The program is distorted at times. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002091243387)
    - Act II. Master copy, undated; 1; 00:52:53; Static and pops in the audio can be heard. The program is distorted at times. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002091243395)
    - Act III, 1960 May 16; 1; 00:30:57; The program is distorted at times. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002091243403)
    - Act I. German text continued, undated; 1; 00:11:58; A high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 25, Item barcode 39002091243411)
    - Act I. German text, copy, undated; 1; 00:49:31; A high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 25, Item barcode 39002091243429)
    - Act I. Second performance, undated; 1; 00:59:25 (Box 25, Item barcode 39002091243437)
    - Act II. Premiere, undated; 1; 00:50:04; High frequency background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 26, Item barcode 39002091243445)
    - Act III. Premiere, undated; 1; 00:32:54 (Box 26, Item barcode 39002091243452)
      7.5 ips, full track
    - Act I. Copy, undated; 1; 01:00:02; A high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 26, Item barcode 39002091243460)
    - Act II. Copy, undated; 1; 00:52:54; A high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. (Box 27, Item barcode 39002091243478)
    - Act III. Copy, undated; 1; 00:31:02; The program is distorted at times. (Box 27, Item barcode 39002091243486)
  - Other Papers
    - Photographs, 1956-1962, undated (Box 28, Folder 176-177)
    - Programs, 1955-1963 (Box 28, Folder 178-179)
    - Clippings, circa 1957-circa 1962 (Box 28, Folder 180-181)
- Other Papers, 1947-1985, undated; Series III; 2.09; (9 boxes)
  Organized into five subseries: Music by Louise Talma, Music by Other Composers, Writings by Thornton Wilder, Clippings, and Unsorted Materials.
  - Music by Louise Talma, 1947-1980, undated
    Autograph manuscript by Louise Talma (diazo reproduction), unless otherwise noted
    - All the Days of My Life (cantata). Score, with manuscript annotations, 1963 June 5; (2 copies) (Box 29 (Oversize), Folder 182-183)
    - All the Days of My Life (cantata). Parts (clarinet, cello, percussion), copyist's manuscript, diazo reproduction, with manuscript annotations, undated (Box 29 (Oversize), Folder 184)
    - Celebration (chorus, SSAA, and orchestra). Score, 1977 July 16-August 4 (Box 29 (Oversize), Folder 185)
    - Diadem (tenor, flute, clarinet, violin, cello, and piano). Score, 1980 June 21; (2 copies) (Box 29 (Oversize), Folder 186-187)
    - String Quartet. Score, with manuscript annotations, 1954 Jan-Aug; (2 copies) (Box 29 (Oversize), Folder 188-189)
    - String Quartet. Parts, with manuscript annotations, 1954 Jan-Aug; (2 copies) (Box 29 (Oversize), Folder 190-191)
    - Summer Sounds (clarinet quintet). Score, with manuscript annotations, 1969 July-1973 February; (8 copies) (Box 30 (Oversize), Folder 192-195)
    - Summer Sounds (clarinet quintet). Parts (fragments from score), 1969 July-1973 February (Box 30 (Oversize), Folder 196)
    - Summer Sounds (clarinet quintet). Parts, with manuscript annotations, 1969 July-1973 February (Box 30 (Oversize), Folder 197)
    - A Time to Remember (chorus and orchestra). Parts (violin I, violin II, viola, percussion), copyist's manuscript, diazo reproduction (transparencies), 1967-1968 (Box 30 (Oversize), Folder 198)
    - A Time to Remember. Chorus and orchestra. Parts (orchestra), copyist's manuscript, diazo reproduction, with manuscript annotations, undated (Box 30 (Oversize), Folder 199-200)
    - Toccata (orchestra). Score, printed (American Music Center), c1947; (6 copies) (Box 31 (Oversize), Folder 201-202)
    - Voices of Peace (chorus and string orchestra). Parts, transparencies, 1973 (Box 32 (Oversize), Folder 203)
    - Voices of Peace (chorus and string orchestra). Parts (fragments from score), 1973 (Box 32 (Oversize), Folder 204)
    - Unidentified. Fragment, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 32 (Oversize), Folder 205)
    - Music notebook (blank), undated (Box 32 (Oversize), Folder 206)
  - Music by Other Composers, 1970, undated
    - Boulanger, Nadia. Faust et Hélène (cantata). Printed (Paris: Editions Durand); inscribed by unidentified, copyright 1970 (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 207)
    - Levin, Robert D., and Martin, Louis. Keyboard Harmony: a Progressive Method in the Harmonization of Figured Basses and Melodies. Manuscript, diazo reproduction; inscribed by Levin, copyright 1970 (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 208)
    - Martin, Louis. An Anthology of Music for Sight-Singing. Manuscript, diazo reproduction; inscribed by Martin, copyright 1970 (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 209)
    - Vidal, Paul. Keyboard Harmony: 178 Figured Basses. Manuscript, diazo reproduction, undated (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 210)
  - Writings by Thornton Wilder, 1953-1973 and undated
    - "Childhood: A Play" (printed), 1960 November (Box 34, Folder 211)
    - "Giordano Bruno's Last Meal in Finnegans Wake" (typescript, with manuscript annotations), undated (Box 34, Folder 212)
    - "Joyce and the Modern Novel" (printed clipping), undated (Box 34, Folder 213)
    - Seven One Act Plays for Four Actors. Bernice (typescript carbons, inscribed), 1957 July 22; (2 copies) (Box 34, Folder 214)
    - Speech on accepting the Peace Prize from the Association of German Publishers and Booksellers (typescript carbon), 1957 October 6 (Box 34, Folder 215)
    - Theophilus North. "Deer Park" (typescript photocopy, revised, with inscription), 1973 March 6 (Box 34, Folder 216)
    - Unsorted articles (printed clippings), undated (Box 34, Folder 217)
  - Clippings
    - Talma, Louise, circa 1955-circa 1976 (Box 35, Folder 218)
    - Talma, Louise, and Thornton Wilder, 1976 (Box 35, Folder 219)
    - Wilder, Thornton, circa 1952-circa 1978, undated (Box 35, Folder 220-226)
    - Unsorted clippings, circa 1957-1973, undated (Box 35, Folder 227-228)
  - Unsorted Materials
    - Photographs of Louise Talma, Thornton Wilder, and others, 1956-1962 (Box 36, Folder 229)
    - Pressed leaves and tree bark, undated (Box 36, Folder 230-231)
    - Printed material about Louise Talma, 1963-1985 (Box 36, Folder 232)
    - Printed Material about Thornton Wilder, 1955-1976, undated (Box 36, Folder 233)
    - Other Printed Material, 1955-1969 (Box 36, Folder 234)
    - Oversize printed material about Louise Talma, undated (Box 37 (Oversize), Folder 235)